<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Politicks of malecontents shewing the grand influence the Jesuits have in all their desperate undertakings</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55318</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13736456</idno>
  <idno type="VID">101628</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240895252</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8524</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13736456</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 847:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Politicks of malecontents shewing the grand influence the Jesuits have in all their desperate undertakings</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Kidgell and are to be sold by Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Jesuits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101628:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101628:1"/>
            <p>THE POLITICKS OF Malecontents, SHEWING The GRAND INFLUENCE THE JESUITS Have in all their DESPERATE UNDERTAKINGS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Kidgell,</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>Richard Janeway.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101628:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101628:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE POLITICKS OF Malecontents, SHEWING The GRAND INFLUENCE THE JESUITS Have in all their DESPERATE UNDERTAKINGS. I.</hi> When there happens any difference between Princes, they must be encouraged therein, and if need be assistance is covertly to be promised to them, and when they are sufficiently engaged then the best advantage is to be made of them.</head>
            <p>ANno 1607. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Fifth</hi> and the State of <hi>Venice</hi> were at great difference, and being embroyled, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> (by the contrivance of our Sacred College) the better to advance their own interest, and to make profit of those divisions, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand cast Oyl into the Fire, though openly they made shew to extinguish it; for on the one side, they encouraged the <hi>Venetians</hi> to maintain their rights; and on the other, they commanded the Governors of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Milan</hi> to serve the Pope with all their power.</p>
            <p>But it's no prudence to stand so near a great person as to be oppressed with his ruine; nor so far off but when his ruine comes, a wise man may be able time enough to rise upon some part of his ruines; when a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101628:3"/> Tempest overthrows a great Tree every one tears off a branch; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you must like the Crab keep the door of the Oyster; make what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage you can when opportunity serves, and you must not be nice in taking advantages; Interest is that which leads the World in a string; imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Hawk which flyes high, yet will descend to catch its's Prey, whereas the Lark in its flight doth nothing but sing.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Kings</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Princes</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be made aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, That by Pois<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is most safe and secure from discovery; <hi>Agathocles</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with a Tooth-pick; <hi>Joan Albreta</hi> Queen of <hi>Navar</hi> was to be poisoned with a perfumed pair of Gloves; and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> with a Pomander; You may compose your Dose of such Ingredients, as shall have their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects at what tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u please.</p>
            <p>There are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty Methods of poysoning found out, you may take out of the Inventory such as as are most fit for present use.</p>
            <p>There may be some difficulty to get admission into the presence of a great Person; but opportunities must be taken and contrivances used; when there was a design to kill <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange, Anno</hi> 1584. <hi>Balthasar Gerrard</hi> was imployed by our Holy Conclave to that purpose, who brought a Seal (which we had the Art to get for him) from Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> to be delivered to the Prince which gave him admission, and gained him Credit with the Prince and an Advantage to assassinate him, which he did.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dominican Fryar,</hi> feigning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have Lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of great concern to be delivered unto King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> was brought into his presence, and kindly received, he delivered his Letters; as the King was reading them, he thrust a poisoned knife into his bowels, of which wound he dyed within few hours after.</p>
            <p>If you design th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Assassination of any gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Person, you may imploy some Instrument to effect it, and then give notice to him of the Assas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sination intented against him, and by whom; as <hi>Varade Rector</hi> of the <hi>Jesuits College</hi> in <hi>Clermount</hi> gave notice to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> That <hi>Peter Barier</hi> intended to assassinate his Majesty (though the said <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> was to that purpose imployed by him) by this means you will gain credit and confidence from and admission to the Prince, and so you may easily effect your designs.</p>
            <p>After you have committed the Fact, retire and put your selves into a disguise; and immediately go to the place where the Assassination was committed, and make a great bussel as any in the throng to find out the Assassin, as <hi>James Michel</hi> the <hi>Scot</hi> did when he had discharged his Pistol at the Person of the Arch-bishop of St. <hi>Andrew, Anno</hi> 1668; and be sure you charge your Enemies with the Fact; this will render them odious, and make your selves famous.</p>
            <p>As it ought to be your care that <hi>Heretical Painces</hi> be humbled, so you must be watchful that no <hi>Catholick Prince</hi> doth too much taper up, and agrandize himself; for then is the <hi>Papal Interest</hi> most safe, when the Forces and Strength of <hi>Princes</hi> are not greatly unequal; for his Holiness
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101628:3"/> then by declaring on either side will assuredly keep all in Peace, and may drive on his own Interest out of that quarter, where the wind blows fairest for his advantage; you know it hath been the wisdom of our holy <hi>Conclave,</hi> That when any <hi>Prince</hi> grows great and potent to pluck off his Feathers, setting up some Neighbouring Princes to be his Enemies, and using all means and methods which may induce him to supplicate his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness for aid and mediation.</p>
            <p>You must have a watchful Eye over <hi>France,</hi> our Congregation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Faith is not well pleased with the <hi>French</hi> Kings designs; his purchase of <hi>Cassal</hi> hath created some Jealousies in our <hi>Supreme Council,</hi> That his purposes are not very Evangelical.</p>
            <p>Our Missionaries gave us to understand, That the most <hi>Christian King</hi> intends the next Campane to carry <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Paris;</hi> and make his Holiness instead of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Vicar a <hi>French Curate;</hi> therefore you must have <hi>Bria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s hands to oppose his Designs, as well as <hi>Argus</hi>'s Eyes to penetrate his Councils, otherwise without the help of <hi>Galilaeus</hi>'s Prospective, we can foresee that his Holiness will be brought from his <hi>Porphery Chair</hi> to the <hi>Stool</hi> of <hi>Repentance;</hi> for there is an old <hi>Prophecy</hi> lately found in the <hi>Vatican.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Cum cantat Gallus, flebit Petrus.</q>
            <p n="3">III. Where a King or Prince is illustrious for his eminent Vertues and goodness, and no <hi>Faults</hi> or <hi>Crimes</hi> can be charged on him, it will be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to charge the Government; you must do as a well experienced Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with a Fort (who not battering the Walls) undermine the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being sure that the batlements and walls will all fall at once, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hazard to himself; the foundation of a State is Power, riches and reputation, you must undermine these, and then you effect your ends.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Heretical Kingdoms</hi> are to be ruffled and put into disorder, for they are inrolled in the Popes black Book for destruction; burning and firing of houses in great Cities and Towns are the most hopeful ways and best Expedients.</p>
            <p>Your attempts upon <hi>London</hi> in 1666 by Fireballs was a glorious Act, but it was ineffectual to the main design; therefore that great City, being the Magazine for Power and Strength of the Nation, must by all your arts be first attacked, that being reduced all will be our own, for the whole Nation will follow the Fate of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plague is a severe Judgment of God, but the Hereticks worse; for so many Hereticks, so many Plagues; the Plague only infects the Body, but Heresie, like the <hi>Italian,</hi> kills Body and Soul; therefore what his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness cannot do by the Sword of the Spirit; you (being the <hi>Janizaries</hi> of the Church militant) must effect by your Arts; proceed in Gods name in this Apostolick work; you may put on Saint <hi>Peters</hi> breast plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, but you must know that in all Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Armory, there is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101628:4"/> no back-piece; you must therefore be resolved to carry on your designs with a high hand, let the Laws of God or the Land say what they will to the contrary.</p>
            <p>I have hinted these things unto you, that you may be invigorated and impowred to proceed couragiously, and remember that after you have raised the storm, you must resolve not to cease the Tempest, till you have blown up the Government in Church and State, Root and Branch.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> is the best Expedient to advance the <hi>Catholick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest;</hi> for under that Spiritual shield you may preserve your selves; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will be convenient to proclaim Spiritual Liberty, and to reduce Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and in other Heretical Kingdoms into so many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, that nothing may unite them in a solid Body to oppose our designs; but if any interest as a mighty stream shall happen to run cross, you must cut it into several channels and small rivolets to make it fordable for the ascent of the triple Crown,</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conscience</hi> in the Church will assuredly introduce arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power in the State; for <hi>Liberty</hi> being once indulged, the Religion of the Country will presently be dwindled into Factions and Parties, and every Faction being in a State of hostility against the other, the Prince for the security of the publick Peace will be enforced to keep up an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; therefore after you have framed new <hi>Phainomena</hi>'s of Religion in the one, you may with good success compose new Schemes of Justice, and new Rules of Government according to the Institutes of Tyranny in the other; and when a Nation is weakned by Factions and infeebled by vitious habits, they are then sufficiently prepared, and made capable to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and a corrupt State is only proper for a Tyrant to rise in.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. The agrandizing of a City and the Suburbs of it are of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to advance the Catholick Designs, for there they may lodge their own party (without the least suspition) to drive on any design; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a great City is the fittest Engine to turn an old Monarchy into a new Commonwealth; therefore our sacred Conclave hath conceived (of which you may make good use) that it's more safe for a State to have three great Cities in it of equal power, that in case one should rebel the other two might ballance, and give Law to the third.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. If any <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> shall be obstinate and not give Obedience to the Pope (by whom Kings reign) then it will be meritorious to bring him into hatred with other Princes, evil Reports must be given out of him, he must be declared a Heretiek, deprived of his Scepter and his Subjects encouraged to arm against him, if these devises will not do, then he must be done away by poison or otherwise.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Conradus</hi> claiming the Soveraignty of <hi>Sicily,</hi> which did much displease the Pope, his Holiness to be revenged of him, defamed the said
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101628:4"/>
               <hi>Conrade,</hi> accused him of Heresie, laid murder to his charge, burthened him with the death, and poysoning of his own Brother, thereby to make him odious to the World; and having murthered his reputation, gave away his Kingdom of <hi>Sicily</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> you see how dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous his Holiness was in that excellent Science of Calumny, it makes us think that the <hi>Florentine</hi> (the best modern Critick of Polity) drew that arrow (of <hi>audacter caluminare</hi>) out of his Holinesses's Quiver.</p>
            <p>And Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> did like himself, who having conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a displeasure against <hi>Frederick Barbarosa</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to undertake a War against the <hi>Turk,</hi> which he did; and being imployed in that War for the good of Christendom, his Holyness signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by his Letters unto the <hi>Sultan,</hi> that he could have no peace while the Emperor lived, and therefore advised to kill him, and to that purpose sent him the Emperors Picture, and from time to time gave notice to the <hi>Sultan</hi> of the Emperors quarters, by which means he was surprised, but the <hi>Sultan</hi> being no friend to his Holiness acquainted his Imperial Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty with all things, and gave him his Picture and Letters which he had received from the Pope, and being set at liberty he assembled the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and there shewed them the Popes Letters and the Picture, which he had sent to the <hi>Sultan:</hi> but the holy Father to excuse himself, order'd three <hi>Fellows</hi> to swear, That the Emperor had imployed three Persons to assassinate him; so that according to his Holinesses Politicks, if any person shall charge you with a Crime, you may safely recriminate him with another; whether it be true or false it matters not it will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press a Gallantry in you, and it will abate the malignity of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation; howsoever it's a good piece of prudence always to be provided with some cunning Strategem, either to bafle your Enemies, or to secure your self and own Interest.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Conspiracies</hi> and <hi>Works of Darkness</hi> must be communicated only by word of mouth, and that singly, for nothing is more dangerous and fatal to great Undertakings, than to commit them to Paper, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them to many.</p>
            <p>The Dukes of <hi>Exeter,</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> and others conspiring to seize upon <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and to restore <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> who was lately deposed; the <hi>Conspirators</hi> did draw up <hi>Articles</hi> between them for their more faithful carrying on the Design; but the Duke of <hi>York</hi> discovering of a <hi>Paper</hi> (wherein the said <hi>Articles</hi> were written) in the Duke of <hi>Exeter</hi>'s bosom seized upon it, and discovered the whole <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth;</hi> which was the ruin and confusion of the <hi>Conspirators;</hi> if the <hi>Paper</hi> had not been discovered in all probability <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> had been seized on, and <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> restored to his Crown and Dignity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Severus</hi> the <hi>Emperor</hi> being to make War against <hi>Niger,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>East,</hi> he conceived it not safe for him to depart from <hi>Rome</hi> till he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a Friendship with <hi>Albinus</hi> a <hi>Britain</hi> (a gallant person) which he did: then <hi>Severus</hi> marched with his Army into the <hi>East</hi> against <hi>Niger,</hi> the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101628:5"/>
               <hi>Roman Senate</hi> having a great affection for <hi>Albinus,</hi> many of the <hi>Senators</hi> writ to him to come to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to take possession of it in <hi>Severus</hi>'s absence, and that they would adhere to him: <hi>Severus</hi> having effected his business in the <hi>East</hi> returns to <hi>Rome,</hi> falls out with <hi>Albinus,</hi> and in <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> gives battle and defeats him, his Cabinet was taken, wherein were many secret Letters to him from the <hi>Senate</hi> and other <hi>Noble Persons</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of him, and disfavour of <hi>Severus:</hi> this did so incense <hi>Severus</hi> that it cost many of them their heads, the loss of their Estates, and the ruin of themselves and Families.</p>
            <p>The Letter which was to be delivered to the Lord <hi>Mountagle,</hi> instead of blowing up the <hi>Parliament,</hi> blew up all the hopes and designs of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in <hi>England:</hi> and how fatal the Letters were which were sent by the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> (our great Friend) unto the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (during the holy League and by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>France</hi> intercepted) we need not tell you, therefore you must be close in your Enterprises, apprehensive of all advantages, and speedy in execution; for all designs, if once made known, they are like mines discovered of no use: Secresy and celerity are the two wheels on which all great Actions move: you must manage your designs so, that they may like white powder (as it is said) do execution without report: The Fish may be taken with the bait, without disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the hook.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Seeds of <hi>Emulation</hi> and <hi>Dissention</hi> must be sowed amongst Princes, that after the example of those Brethren which sprung out of the Serpents Teeth, they may destroy one another; therefore <hi>Sejanus</hi> (to make dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sention the Ladder to clime up to the Empire) set variance betwixt <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> to the end that the one should take occasion to destroy the other: and the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> when he designed to set the Crown of <hi>France</hi> upon his own head, living King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> proffered the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>France</hi> to the King of <hi>Navar</hi> next Heir to that Crown, not out of any kindness to him, but to breed such distrust and jealousies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Kings; that the one might let slip no occasion that might prove the destruction and overthrow of the other, and so the Duke might the better drive on his own designs and purposes to obtain that Crown. And you must take notice that all Wars raised between <hi>Catholick Princes</hi> are by us contrived to be but as decoys to draw <hi>Heretical Princes</hi> into ruine and destruction, and are by us used as delusory mediums drawn before their Eyes, that we may more securely advance the designs of our Supreme Council: You must make it your work to set Friends at Jars, Allies at Variance, and Confederates at Dissention.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101628:5"/>XI. It will be a great Instance of prudence to wind your selves into Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors and the Chief Ministers of State: you may represent in what disguise you please the particular State of affairs abroad, which you may make to appear white, when they are black; clear, when cloudy; and <hi>e contra,</hi> as most subservient to your ends: these notices being prudently communicated, many times beget differences between Princes, howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they will create Jealousies.</p>
            <p>By Orders of our Supreme Council, Twelve Jesuites (the most consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for their happy conduct of affairs) were sent into <hi>Holland</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the <hi>Dutch,</hi> That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> designed to make himself King of the United Provinces, which did so influence and alarm the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Mogans</hi> (for they dread nothing more than a King) that they forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with begged Peace of his most Christian Majesty, which was granted to them; and thereby the Alliance of the Confederates was broken, and such a Feud was raised between the Prince and the States, and such jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies amongst all the Confederates, that he thought himself happy, that upon any Terms he could obtain Peace, which assuredly would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered the Empire, if the most Christian King by the segacity and contrivance of our sacred Consistory. had not been disappointed in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses: therefore you may observe of what admirable consequence these Arts are of, if managed with prudence: it matters not whether your Information be true or false: it will have the same effect, if you take your measures right.</p>
            <p>The Holy Father of <hi>Rome</hi> doth many times to good purpose disseminate differences between the Marquess of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> the <hi>Landsgrave</hi> of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssen,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> the Duke of <hi>Brunswick,</hi> the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine</hi> and other Princes and States in <hi>Europe,</hi> and being full of fears and jealousies amongst themselves, they rarely can effect any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Papal Interest, for their weakness is his Strength, and where his Holiness cannot establish his own power, he endeavours to give dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance and disquiet to all others.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Enthusiastical Raptures and Pretences of Divine Inspirations are of great use to advance interest and carry on designs.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Celestine</hi> being chosen Pope (but a simple Person) <hi>Boniface</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives a Tube by which in the night he did send a voice into his Chamber, signifying to his Holiness, That he was an Angel sent from Heaven, and had command to order him to leave the Popedom, and retire to such an Island, and there live in his solitude the remainder of his Life, which at first disturbed his Holiness; but hearing the voice and command three times he consulted with some of the Cardinals, which had a desire to be rid of him, and to have <hi>Boniface</hi> Pope, they told him it could be no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101628:6"/> delusion, hearing it three times, but a Message from Heaven, and therefore advised him to give over his charge and obey the command, which he did; and <hi>Boniface</hi> was afterwards elected Pope, and called <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>Eight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomets</hi> Falling Sickness was of great use to him, for he pretended those fits were nothing but heavenly Raptures, in which he conversed with the Angel <hi>Gabriel;</hi> his Pidgeon, which he taught to feed at his Ear, he gave out to be the Holy Ghost (by whom he was instructed in the Law which he was to publish) made his <hi>Alcoron</hi> Oraculer, the Holy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Maid of <hi>Orleans</hi> beat the <hi>English</hi> out of <hi>France,</hi> and those devout Raptures of <hi>Kemitius</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> regained him his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the <hi>Picts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you have concluded of any mischievous Design, for a blind to the people, you must appoint a day of humiliation to enquire of God, what is to be done.</p>
            <p>Pious <hi>Frauds</hi> are of excellent use to promote any Design, a holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious pretence will authenticate the most hellish enterprize; and it will make you smile to observe how the people will be taken with the gaiety of a godly pretence.</p>
            <p>Therefore that prosperous cheat, the pretension to Holiness and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inspirations must be carefully preserved; and all succesful wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness must be referred to the impulses of the Spirit, Return of Prayer, or Calls of Providence; the People are ductile, and easily drawn to any design, when they think Heaven is in the Plot, and God is one Party thereof; therefore,
<q>
                  <l>—Quoties vis fallere Plebem,</l>
                  <l>Finge Deum—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing did more insinuate the Laws of King <hi>Minos</hi> into the <hi>Cretans,</hi> than the pretence of his Dialogue with <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and the Holy Father St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> our glorious Founder left a Journal or Writing, how things pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed between the Holy Ghost and Himself, and the Visions are there set down wherewith he was inspired, when he made his Constitutions, which have inworthyed them to all Posterity; this religious Simplicity and holy Reverence of Heaven in the minds of the people must be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished; for it is the first Step to facilitate and promote mischievous Designs.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101628:6"/>XIII. It will be prudence to use all endeavours to insinuate your selves into the Priests, and to make so many of them as you can to your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to serve ends, they will be of great use; for no Heresie, Schism or Rebellion can spread or get footing in a Nation but by them; for these are the Men which are best able to drive on any design, they have a great influence upon the People, and what they say or do it passes for Oracular, and is thought worthy to be followed, they rule over the Conscience which is the Rudder that steers the actions and thoughts of men, and they can turn it as the wind blows for their advantage, they can make the beast with many heads conceive according to the colour of those rods they use to cast before them.</p>
            <p>Therefore they who have the Priests on their side may easily draw the rest of the people after them; there hath been rarely any distemper in a State, which hath not been derived from, or advanced by, them: when <hi>Isabel</hi> Queen of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had raised an Army against the King her Husband, the Bishop of <hi>Hereford</hi> (the better to countenance the business) preached before her and her Army, and took his Text out of the 2 <hi>Kings chap.</hi> 24. <hi>My Head aketh;</hi> who concluded, that an aking and sick Head of a Kingdom was of necessity to be taken off, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to be cured; you see what an excellent gift the cogging of a Dye is, to make the word speak what they please; though this was a rotten Doctrine, yet being well gilt and varnished, it served to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse the credulity of the people, and to justifie the Iniquity of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there is no mask becomes innovation or rebellion so well as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this sanctifies the most pernitious designs; let the enterprise be as black as Hell, if it be influenced by a Euminary of the Church, with the help of a spiritual <hi>fucus,</hi> it will seem to the Opticks of the vulgar as white as innocency; all the floods of misery have been much swelled by their Holy-water: The times under <hi>Dioclesian</hi> were <hi>Pagan,</hi> under <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine Christian,</hi> under <hi>Constantius Arrian,</hi> under <hi>Julian Apostate,</hi> under <hi>Jovinian Christian</hi> again: And all these changes and alterations from the influence of the Priests; there cannot be better Trumpets in the World to raise up Rebellion or Sedition than they; the preaching <hi>Fryars</hi> and <hi>Monks</hi> were the Chief Incendiaries of the <hi>Catalonians</hi> to their revolt, <hi>Hernado de Auralos,</hi> and <hi>Juan de Padilla</hi> in the <hi>Spanish</hi> Civil Wars against <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth</hi> imployed some <hi>Friars</hi> to rail against the Government in their Pulpits, and so to stir up the people to war, which according to expectation took fire in <hi>Toledo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore you may observe of what grand concern it is to have the Priests our Friends; what cometh from the Pulpit, the people look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Oracles of Heaven, when many times they are nothing but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion of Impostors; therefore you must imploy your care to engage such as are hopeful and well affected to us and our enterprise.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101628:7"/>XIV. It will be discretion sometimes to keep touch in small matters, the better to deceive in matters of great concern: therefore the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> when he intended a Rebellion against <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and to set the Crown on his own Head advised all his Friends and Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, That they should shew their Obedience in small things, and in matters of no moment to the <hi>French</hi> King, that they might be trusted in matters of more weight and profit, to the furtherance of his and their designs: It will be no advantage to be over honest, you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve just men grow lean and poor by their Integrity: and such as inrich themselves with publick spoils, and eat out the very bowels of a Nation wax fat.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Great persons must not be touched, if they be, they must be made sure from taking revenge.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Alexander</hi> did justly in putting <hi>Philotas</hi> to death, because if he had pardoned him, it would have inabled him to have attempted new Treasons against him, when it would not have been in his power to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them; where a man of courage is accused and imprisoned, it's more dangerous to absolve him, than to condemn him, and nothing is more dangerous than to bring a great courage to the place of Execution, and then grant him his Pardon; for he will always remember the affront and forget the pardon: <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> of <hi>France</hi> being advised to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Marshal <hi>Byron,</hi> said well, <hi>That a Firebrand casts more Flame and Smoak without a Chimney than within it, Dion</hi> being banished <hi>Syracuse</hi> by <hi>Dionitius Junior,</hi> and <hi>Cariolanus</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> they made most bloody Wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their own Country; but dead men make no War; <hi>Carminiola</hi> Captain General of the <hi>Venetians</hi> army, having defeated the Duke of <hi>Milan</hi>'s Forces, they finding that he was but cold in the prosecution of the War; they thought it not prudence to cashier him; for then they might lose what they had gotten, but conceived the safer course was to put him to death, which they did: The <hi>Carthaginians (Amilcar</hi> their General having concluded a Peace with <hi>Agathocles</hi> the <hi>Syracusan,</hi> which did much displease them) did forbear publickly to condemn him, whilst he was in command; yet they passed their Sentence against him in the <hi>Senate</hi>) and sealed it up in their <hi>Urn,</hi> not to be made known till he returned to a private condition: It is an Oracle of Truth, <hi>That the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle course in Cases of Extremity is always dangerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101628:7"/>XVI. If you design the Ruin of any great Person that stands in your way, you must whisper amongst the Populacy some approbious accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against him, as it were privately, by this seeming Suppression, men impatient of Secrecy will more eagerly divulge it, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger will appear the greater by an affected silence, the Calumnies and Suspitions must be so contrived, that they may force the party to some course in his own defence, and by securing himself increase the publick fears, and then he may safely be destroyed.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII When a People are disposed to Faction, force Unites them, whereas if they be left to themselves, they will fall into civil Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: This is manifest in the late distempers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. After you are perfectly instructed by what means an Heriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal State hath attained unto Grandeur cross their Councils and Designs in the use of those means, and you will assuredly bring destruction to it.</p>
            <p>If a State doth support its Credit by the general Reputation of its Riches, as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> by his Wealth from the <hi>Indies,</hi> let it be shew'd that it's poor and needy, and let it's Wealth be Intercepted; are there wise Governours and Magistrates placed in the Dominions to contain the Subjects in Obedience, and Neighbours in fear? send Fire-Brands, and Authors of Sedition amongst the Subjects of that State.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. Nothing doth more advance Interest then the shadow of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but the Reality of it doth many times hurt; therefore you must be able to make use of Religion to serve your ends, and to lay it aside, as need shall require; never intend any good beyond appearance; you may pretend Affection to Religion, not thereby to Contract a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with Heaven; but that you may more easily carry on designs, you must use Religion for a Styrup to get into the Sadle, and so upon the back of Honour, not as <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder to Climb up to Heaven by; injoy you the Temporal Blessings and Advantages of Religion, let others expect a Crown and the Land of Promise.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101628:8"/>
            <p>The Glory of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> grew up by the Popes taking upon them the Honour to be <hi>Vindices Canonum;</hi> the strickt Preservers of the Antient Discipline of the Church, which took extreamly well with the People, till in the end from being chief Labourers in the Vineyard, the became Landlords, which was the Honour aimed at; and at last obtained by <hi>Boniface,</hi> whom <hi>Phocas</hi> made head of the Church; and it may be truly said, that they have as great command now, under the pretence of Religion, as ever they had formerly by force of Arms, so truly was it said by <hi>Prosper of Acquitaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Roma Caput Mundi quicquid non possidet armis,</l>
               <l>Religione tenet—.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="20">XX. When any unwarrantable Action is in design, for the better affecting of it, the People must be made, and fit Instruments prepared; the Duke of <hi>Mayen</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> had never contained the Rable in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to him, had he not used the Help and Furtherance of <hi>Martal Campan, Nally, Rowland</hi> and <hi>Bassy</hi> the Priests, Instruments of his fury and Misleaders of the Ignorant and Seditious Multitude; the People are the Anvil whereon all sorts of Hammers strike, its a work of no difficulty to perswade them to any thing (especially if it be hallowed and influenced by a Holy Star) you may like <hi>Orpheus</hi> draw the brutish Vulgar (most capable of Sedition) to Dance after whatsoever they are tuned unto) especially if they be skrewed up to the hopes of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they never see behind the Curtain.</p>
            <p>A deep contrivance agrees not with the impatience of the Vulgar, to whom speedy undertakings seem always most Heroick; slow yet sure practices, are interpreted by them as the motion of false and base spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; but nothing prevails with them more then the hope of gain; if you shall be Obliged to disburse Money to them, you must use it as Anglers do their Fish to catch more, It will be the test of Prudence to deal with the Instruments of your designs, as men do by their Candles, burn them to the Snuff, and then having lighted another, tread that under foot, and after you have effected your ends, you must forget the bosom which warmed you.</p>
            <p n="21">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101628:8"/>XXI. Give a fair Compliance to the times wherein you live; <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita est omnis homo;</hi> to pass a dangerous Wood safely, its lawful to put on such skins as the beasts have which haunt those Woods, if the Hill will not come to <hi>Mahomet, Mahomet</hi> will go to the Hill; you need not boggle at the taking of any Oath, or going to Church, or receiving the Sacrament; Church Papists and Catholicks in <hi>Mascorade</hi> may high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to the Catholick Interest.</p>
            <p>You must learn to swallow down Oaths with as much celerity as <hi>Lazarello de Tormes</hi> could a <hi>Saucidge;</hi> if you will bring your designes into a safe harbour, you must swear as the Tide serves; streatch your conscience rather than loose your Interest; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitate the old Marquess of <hi>Winchester,</hi> rather bow then break; Perjury and Hypocrisy are the only Clymax by which men ascend to Grandeur; The <hi>Grecian Lysander</hi> was in the right, when he said that Oaths were invented to deceive men, as false play Children; and it was a good rule of the <hi>Priscil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jura, Perjura, secretum prodere noli:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Swear and forswear,</l>
                  <l>But from discovering your Designs forbear.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>You must always be provided with some running Subterfuge and Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to elude any thing which may invade your Interest, or impeach your Reputation and Credit.</p>
            <p>Get to be always of the prevailing Faction; a zealous Professor of the Opinions in fashion; disguise all your Actions with a Religious Dress; put on the white Robe of Innocency, to conceal the blackness of your Attempts; your words must be put in a spiritual Quirpo, and <hi>Protheus</hi> like assume that shape which is most in Grace, and of most profitable conducement to your ends: you may imitate the Cat in the Epologue, who being transformed into a <hi>Gentlewoman,</hi> when a Mouse came by made at it. and catched it, so let your Garb and Dress be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so fine and religious in appearance, if any prey comes in your way you know what you have to do.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. Make use of Libels, false Reports, and Acusations, which are alwayes Proemial to destruction and Ruine, for they are excellent Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in the hands of a cunning Artist to carry on designes, blot the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of any person (who thereby is rendred Contemtable and Odious) Destruction will easily follow; by this Art the Abbots and Fryers (the best of men) in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights Reign were ruined in <hi>England;</hi> the Templars in the time of <hi>Philip</hi> the Fair of <hi>France</hi> were destroyed, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101628:9"/> their order Supprest; if the person which is to be Supplanted cannot be attacked with down right battery by reason of his Grandure or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, if you cannot take the main Fort, try if you can possess your selves of the out Works, raise some prejudice against his Discretion or other parts, and if you can bring him into Contempt you have done your work; thus they dealt with <hi>Socrates</hi> amongst the Antients, when they could not Suppress his Reputation hyred <hi>Aristophanes</hi> a Comick Poet to personate him on the Stage and by insinuation of those interludes insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly conveyed first a contempt then a hatred of him in the hearts of the People.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Ziba</hi> had a purpose to Undermine <hi>Mephiboseth</hi> in his estate; he first practised upon his fame in a false Accusation. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.3.</p>
            <p>You must be dextrous in this Science, it may be of excellent Use; <hi>Cyril</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople</hi> was by Calumnie (our old friend) turned out of his place, and almost by our Arts ruined.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Arians</hi> accused <hi>Eustatius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Antioch</hi> of adultry, and <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> of many other Crimes, to make them Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and you know how the Honour and Reputation of many Eminent Persons during the late troubles in <hi>England,</hi> with this Admirable engine of Calumnie were battered, therefore it is great Wisdom to be Skilful in raising of Slanders, and bold to Prosecute them; for howsoever the wound may be cured; the Scar will still remain.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. When any unjust Action is undertaken and others come into assistances the better to secure them to your party, you must enjoyn them the performance of some Notorious and Villanous Act; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be excluded from all hopes of Pardon.</p>
            <p>And we must tell you this Maxime hath been well observed and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised by Antiquity, for there were certain <hi>Affrican</hi> Souldiers who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing revolted from the Service of <hi>Carthage</hi> and making War against it, and fearing least the Souldiers should be reconciled to <hi>Carthage,</hi> by the advice of <hi>Anthanitus</hi> their General (to prevent all hopes of reconciliation and for their common safety) <hi>Gaser</hi> a great Captain of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> and their prisoner was put to death; that by such a Course every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ingaged in the action; they might understand there was no other hopes left then in Victory alone; Those who assisted <hi>Agathocles</hi> of <hi>Syracuse</hi> in his Tyrany and in those Murders and Spoyles of his fellow Citizens had no other hope of defence then the support of <hi>Agathocles</hi> himself, who had been pertaker with them in their Villanies and Cruelties commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and indeed the best security that Desperate men can deliver to each other is to perform some such Actions as are equally unpardonable to all; there is no better way to make others Adhere to your fortunes, then by winding their Concernments upon the same bottom.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101628:9"/>XXIV. When a person is questioned for any notorious Villany, which he hath committed, its a safe Principle to counterfeit Madness, or else to give the better countenance to the Action; to pretend Conscience, or that it was done to propagate the Faith.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>John de Isle</hi> did like a Polititian who making an Attempt upon <hi>Henry</hi> the Great of <hi>France</hi> at <hi>Pontneif</hi> with a Daggar to have assassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated him, and being Apprehended and brought before the <hi>President Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim</hi> to be Examined, he told the <hi>President</hi> that he was <hi>King</hi> of all the world; and said that <hi>Henry</hi> the great was an Usurper, and had taken the Crown from him, and would chastise him for his Temerity, the good <hi>King</hi> thinking that he was sufficiently punished by his folly commanded he should only be kept in Prison; and <hi>Raviliac</hi> who Assassinated that great <hi>King</hi> pretended that he killed him <hi>in Ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> and that he himself for that Act should receive a <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Martyrdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">XXV. At all marts of business you must have your Factors though they do not seem openly to trade; Secret espiels in all places are neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary; an <hi>Ephemerides</hi> will be of great use to know how the <hi>Orbes</hi> of the Court move; and that you may receive happy Influences from them, you may have intelligence by the assisting <hi>Angells</hi> which give them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. After you have infused principles of Faction and Sedition into the People, then you must try how forward they will be for Action; for which purpose nothing will be more convenient than the Agitation of Tumults; and the better to raise them you must have fit and adapted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments you must tell them, if they be not Zealous the worser partie will have the better of the good partie, and to secure and keep the <hi>Mermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> at your Devotion, they must now and anon too, be alarmed with false Rumours, strange Plots, and designs; they will not only believe such stories but fear the events; you must yet out nothing but Persecution Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, O the cruelty of the <hi>Bishops!</hi> O the Superstition and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the <hi>Clergie!</hi> and all this against the cause of <hi>God,</hi> the souls of the true <hi>Saints,</hi> the peace of the Directory and the happiness of the <hi>Elect</hi> the true Children of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if there be any that shall take distast at the Tumults and that they ought to be suppressed you must tell them, that they must not discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their Freinds.</p>
            <p>Therefore by your arts Tumults must be raised; for raising of Tumults and Disorders are of excellent use to bring confusion to a <hi>Nation,</hi> and by Consequence destruction to it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101628:10"/>
            <p>It was truly observed by <hi>Tasso,</hi>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quando sia di si gran moti il fine,</l>
                     <l>Non fabriche di Regin, ma ruine,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Those rable factious tumults never mend</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Nation, but its ruin doth portend.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Venetians</hi> by the advice and contrivance of our Sacred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. Procured their great Enemy <hi>Ibraim</hi> to be deposed and his eldest Son <hi>Mahomet</hi> to be set up in his stead; this Art of theirs cost the <hi>Prince Visier</hi> his life, and had almost cost the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> his <hi>Empire,</hi> the <hi>Bassa</hi> of <hi>Aleppo</hi> revolted, and all <hi>Asia</hi> fell off, had not the generous <hi>Bassa</hi> of <hi>Damascus</hi> notably met the approching fate, with singular Wisdome and Conduct; and the <hi>Missionaries</hi> of our Order did make such Tumults in <hi>Lublin, Jerostane</hi> and in all <hi>Poland</hi> that they had procured the Ruine of that <hi>Kingdome</hi> and we think <hi>England</hi> hath great reason to Remember us.</p>
            <p>We cannot but Remind you of one excellent Stratagem we had to give trouble to <hi>Rochel</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> that when we could not reduce it to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Catholick Church; we Counterfeited the common Seal of that <hi>Citie,</hi> wherewith we signed our Letters (in which were contained several things destructive to the interest of <hi>France</hi>) which being intercept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by notice from us, and delivered to the <hi>French King,</hi> procured great displeasure from that <hi>King</hi> to <hi>Rochel,</hi> who immediatly invested it with his Army, and brought much misery and callamitie to it; how dextrous and Active we have been in contriving and executing disorders and troubles (to propagate the Faith) <hi>Swethland, France,</hi> the Conspiracies in <hi>England</hi> the tragical end of many Nobles in <hi>Germany,</hi> the troubles in <hi>Venice,</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults in <hi>Moscovia,</hi> distressed <hi>Hungary</hi> oppressed <hi>Styria, Carinthia</hi> &amp;c. can abundantly witness: you must therefore inject such an infection into the Vulgar, that it may rise into the boyles of sedition and so impostumate into a Rebellion: consider the ingenious and dextrous contrivance of our holy <hi>Conclave,</hi> when we raised such disorders in <hi>England;</hi> that in eleaven years there were seaventeen Models of Government and the people there were so Zealously factions, as if they had been so by Predestination.</p>
            <p>The Tub thumpers and custin dusters in the late Distempers there, when the <hi>Popes</hi> bellows to enkindle Flames, and the lungs of the <hi>Vatican</hi> to breath out Sedition, and being agitated by our Emissaries did highly promote the <hi>Catholick</hi> interest, You must therefore make it your study to impregnate the fancy of the Zelots with Enthusiasticall Conceptions, Extatical rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and with a holy Flatus, this will make their immaginations turgent and so apt to long to execute any design that the <hi>Lord</hi> shall put into your Hearts.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101628:10"/>
            <p>What a glorious thing was it to see <hi>Thomas Anello</hi> a poor Fisher-man to rule in <hi>Naples?</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by <hi>Bodadilla</hi> a Cloth-worker at <hi>Medina del Campo,</hi> and by <hi>Vellaria</hi> a Skinner in <hi>Salamanca?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Was it not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful that <hi>Nol Cromwell</hi> sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld he made Protector of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> Was it not admirable that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> a Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor should be declared King of the <hi>Ʋniverse?</hi> these were the offals and rubbish of mankind, and the by-casts of fortune, yet raised to that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi> of glory by the <hi>Sagacity</hi> and Artifice of our sacred Colledge.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Sow what differences you can between great Persons, by that means they may be drawn into Faction to Espouse a bad quarrel to work their Malice; or their private injuries will break out into Hostility to the disturbance of the Publick, as the <hi>Venanides</hi> and <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vaiales</hi> two Noble Families in <hi>Castile</hi> did; the difference between the Duke of <hi>Matalone</hi> (Chief of the Carasses) and Prince of <hi>Sanza,</hi> had almost endangered the Kingdom of <hi>Naples;</hi> and upon what reason the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> Headed a Rebellious Army in the late Troubles of <hi>England,</hi> its well known.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Giving out of News sometimes may to good purpose be Practised; therefore you must have a Mint to coin such News as may be currant and Serviceable to your Ends; and careful to dispierce it, for many times false News to drive on designs; may be as useful as false Prophets were in the Kingdom of <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Papers and Books must be carefully Spread abroad against Popery; Arminianism, Arbitrary Power, grievances and in disfavor of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in Church and State; nothing will prevail more with the many for they will believe any thing they see in Print.</p>
            <p>How Doctor <hi>Laytons</hi> Book called <hi>Sions Plea,</hi> wherein he called the then Queen of <hi>England,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Heth</hi> a <hi>Canaanite</hi> and Idolatress, did gain upon the People we need not tell you.</p>
            <p>There were others then which did admirable service to his Holiness, by the Books they Published, therefore you must be always provided with some Factious and Seditious piece to set forth; as occasion shall require, and then you must have an answer ready to it; one may cry it up, ono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther decry it, (the better to make a Noise and buoy up Schism, or Faction) nay the same Person may be <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> if they please, as father <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> (with good success) many times was; this will amuse People, and distil principles of Faction and Sedition into them, and so prepare them for a Rebellion; you must be another <hi>Peter</hi> the Hermite, to blow the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to a holy War, it will be Meritorious to be a leader in the Spiritual Camp; therefore let it be your Study and care to toll the People into Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Faction, and so to their slavery and destruction, as the Py'd Piper did the Children and Rats of <hi>Hamel; England</hi> is a great Animal, it will never die except it destroys it self; Sedition and Schism are the best Engines to effect it.</p>
            <p>When you come into any Heretick Country, the first things which you must be sure to gain, are liberty of Conscience, and liberty of the Press; by the first you have an Opportunity to blow Fears and Jealousies into the Peoples Heads, and to Collect several distinct Clans, and holy Clubs, to the disturbance of the Publick Peace; by this means you may settle an humor in the People of railing against the Male-administration of affairs; of Vilifying the Supream Powers, and may so Spirit them, that they will be like the <hi>Neopolitan</hi> Courser in <hi>Boccalin,</hi> always ready to cast his Rider; or like <hi>Giotto</hi>'s Ass, still smelling after new Governments.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101628:11"/>
            <p>By the second you have the means of playing the <hi>Ambodexters,</hi> one while taking part with the Conformists, another while Vindicating the Dissenters.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Dangerous Enterprises, the more they are thought on, the less hope they give of good success, and therefore Conspiracies not suddenly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, are for the most part discovered and laid aside.</p>
            <p n="30">30. It will be great prudence to reduce Heretical Churches to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Subjection of that of <hi>Rome,</hi> the best <hi>mediums</hi> to effect it, must be to deface the glory of them with calumnies, telling the People that the Doctrine thereof is Heretical, the Ceremonies are the Liveries of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, Patches of Popery, Episcopacy, and the Service-Book (where they have them) the two Plague-sores of the Church, the Clergy idle, Canonical ignorant, and drunken Common-Prayer-Book-men; this will take well with the People, for in the late Troubles in <hi>England,</hi> when the <hi>Psudo</hi> Zealots planted the Artillery of their depraving tongues against that Church, you know what good success they had, they converted their Churches, in many places, into Stables, and the Fonts were the Wells where they watered their Horses, the Pulpits were the Pantries where they hung up their Meat, and the Communion Tables the Dressers upon which they joynted it.</p>
            <p>The Revenues of the Church must be taken from it, (so the glory of the Church will be rendred contemptible by its Poverty) and the Clergy must be put to Pensions; by that means none shall get preferment but those who will hold forth what their Pay-master shall think fit, and by their Preachments gain Proselytes to any who shall get uppermost; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Archymedes</hi> Engine will advance the Catholick interest.</p>
            <p>You must be careful to hinder and prevent Catechising (for nothing can be more destructive to our interest) as it hath been happily neglected or laid aside for some years, to the great benefit of the Catholick Church; you must mount your Batteries against Episcopacy (which is the only Screen against Schism) and the Bishops which are the Pillars of the Church, must be pulled down as rotten and useless Posts. You know it was a declared Maxim of King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>England, No Bishop, no King;</hi> so if you ruin the first, destruction will presently attend the latter. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, be sure to take away their Votes in the House of Peers, and then you may deal with them as High-way-men do with those they intend to Rob, first Gag them, and then take away what they have, but these things must be acted covertly; it's no prudence to declare the design at first; a plausible pretence is half a Conquest.</p>
            <p>And to deal truly with you, there cannot be a better way to destroy the Church of <hi>England</hi> than to convert the <hi>British</hi> Monarchy into an <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Common-wealth; his Holiness never had such an Harvest (as in the late distempers in <hi>England</hi>) when it was so, the spiritual Seeds-men did then disseminate such principles that they sprouted and came up so prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously (as like the Souldiers of <hi>Cadmus</hi>) they were past all resistance, and yet none know how they took root; the Church of <hi>England</hi> (which is the only fortress against the Papal Interest) by your arts must be branched out, and Cantonized into as many Minute parties and Sects of Religion as may be; this once effected, it will be hard in few Years to tell which is the Church of <hi>England,</hi> neither party being Subordinate to one another, and the Religionaries being so Sedulous to gain Proselites, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101628:11"/> the affections not only of the common People, but of the Gentry and Great Ones, that it highly please us to consider what will be the result and consequence; therefore be sure to cry up Liberty of Conscience (if Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Uniformity be established we are all undone) Petition for a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it (Petitioning being the Saints Birth-right) if you be any waies denied it, or have not a speedy remedy you must take the cure into your own hands; but be sure you be-spatter those of the Clergy which will not joyn with you to advance the glory of the Catholick Church, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them contemptible to the People (this done, that which they shall Preach will be slighted) for these are the Spectacles which give them a sight and knowledge of the Truth; therefore if you will commit a Rape upon the Body of the Church, you must first put out the Lights, as others have done upon the like occasion at their Meetings.</p>
            <p>Howsoever Liberty and Toleration (the Idol of the People, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Popes Mouse-trap to catch the simple, being set up) the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion will undiscernably get footing amongst them; and many of them seeing the Madness and Iniquity of their own Factions and Sects, will hate them, and run from them as far as they can, and so be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks before they know where they are.</p>
            <p>And all the Factions being in a state of Hostility amongst themselves, and labouring to supplant each the other (as without doubt they will) the State will be thereby much enweakened, and any Catholick Prince may attempt on it: But remember, if you cannot establish the Catholick Religion, that you hinder all others by your Arts from setling.</p>
            <p n="31">31. When the People by your Sagacity and Contrivance are multiplyed into Parties and Factions (the better to Distemper and Disorder the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) you must attempt to set up that Glorious Idol (the great <hi>Diana</hi>) of Reformation; or else you must by your Artifice cause something to be imposed upon them which may be ungrateful to them; as the <hi>English</hi> Service-Book was to our good Brethren in <hi>Scotland:</hi> Every Sect, like Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, will be ready to fire at the first touch; one Faction is the best Engine to suppress another: The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (which are a great Party) if wisely managed may be employed to reduce all the other (with Promise of Establishment of their Religion) (though without any intent of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance) which being effected, the other Sectaries must be Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and made use of to give a check to the Prevailing Party, they will be true to the Interest, and faithful to the Service, and nothing can be more acceptable to them than to be Revenged of those who have been their greatest Persecutors. You see how the Church, with a Feather from the same Wing, may be Wounded; and a Coal from the Altar may make a Combustion in the Church and State.</p>
            <p n="32">32. The better to Seduce the People (which are as Tools to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick) and to drive on your Designs, you must compose your selves to all Popular Courses; you must testifie a great Zeal for Religion, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ress the People, some must be cajoled with fair and splendid hopes, others whom you may adjudge fit for business, and whose Slavery may be bought with Profit (when the Catholick Interest shall be established) are to be preferred to such an such Places; and to all you must use proper Attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives (specious in words, and void of any Reality) by those Glorious Pageants the Catholick Interest will be Ascendant, and the Yoke of Slavery will be bound to the Peoples Necks the stronger.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101628:12"/>
            <p>To gather Hands and Subscriptions is a good way to make your Party the more unanimous, and to draw many well-meaning People to be your Disciples; thereby you may see, as in a Political Glass, the strength of your own Party; then you may clamour for Justice, and to have that effected which you had in Projection, as it hath with good success been Practised.</p>
            <p>And we must tell you, that the Catholick Religion can never be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in <hi>England</hi> upon a firm Basis, except you first introduce there an Arbitrary Power, which may be effected by this Medium; there are three States in the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> First, Lords Spiritual, which are the Bishops; Secondly, Lords Temporal; Thirdly, the Commons of <hi>England;</hi> if you can by your Arts seclude the Bishops (as the Non-conforming Brethren have a good mind to it) then as the King and two States ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the third State, so the King and the Lords may exclude the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; this done, the King and one State are remaining, he may at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure dismiss the Lords, and so make himself absolute; for be assured, as long as the three States continue in the Parliament, Popery can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any growth in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>You see what an excellent thing it is to be well seen in this art of State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft; the knack of Petitioning may with good advantage be practised in many cases, for from the contrivance of three or four Privado's, like a Multiplying-glass you may produce many thousands, which will give a great Countenance to many designs.</p>
            <p>The People if well inspired may be taught by their Petitions to speak or desire any thing. It will be prudence in you, if there be a Petition on foot, for any thing which may be prejudicial to your interest to frame a Counter Petition, as they did in <hi>England</hi> in 1642. when some Petitioned the Parliament there for peace; the Godly Party presently drew a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against it, and the better to encourage the Subscribers, gave the poorer sort of them twelve pence apiece, which was prudently contrived by our Sacred Council; what good effects it had <hi>England</hi> can tell you.</p>
            <p n="33">33. To strengthen your own Party, and to weaken the Address, you must work off as many as you can from them to your own side; which may be effected by proffering greater advancement and noble Rewards to them which shall adhere unto you.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, being desirous to alienate the affection of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, from <hi>Francis</hi> the First of <hi>France,</hi> obtained his ends by promising Cardinal <hi>Julio de Medicis</hi> a yearly Pension of 10000 Ducats to be paid to him out of the Archbishoprick of <hi>Toledo;</hi> and by giving <hi>Alexander de Medicis</hi> a Pension of the like value in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marquess of <hi>Mantoa</hi> being General of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Army against <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> was drawn off from their Service with greater offers and a larger Pension than he had of the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore if persons of the greatest Quality have been content to be catched with the Golden Hook, never despair to win and change the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of meaner persons, especially such as are ambitious of Preferments, greedy of Rewards, or have taken occasion of discontent, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so hard but that pernicious metal Gold will penetrate. You know what excellent effects it had at <hi>New-Castle,</hi> which was contrived by <hi>T. C.</hi> the Cardinal's Secretary; this is the best Lure to invite those who seek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101628:12"/> Prey. This made <hi>Pigmalion</hi> King of <hi>Tyre,</hi> kill his Brother-in-law <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus;</hi> for this <hi>Achilles</hi> sold the Corps of valiant <hi>Hector;</hi> and this though upon an Asses back, will take the strongest City in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Destruction surer comes, and rattles louder out of a Mine of Gold than one of Powder.</p>
            <p n="34">34. The Brethren of the Congregations, if you take your measures rightly, may be prevailed with to concur in any action with you.</p>
            <p>For <hi>John Calvin</hi> confirmed his Presbyterian Discipline in the same year that <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the first glorious Founder of the Jesuits, was chosen the first General, <hi>viz.</hi> 1541. and just a hundred years after 1641. did the <hi>Calvenistical</hi> Proselites (being agitated by our Missionaries from the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Conclave) make and create that confusion and calamity in the Church and Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> as you all well know. And as these Orders took their rise together, so they have gone hand in hand in many things ever since; we agree in killing and deposing of Kings; they are all against the King's having any power in Spirituals, and many of them against their having any in Temporals; and they give as blind an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Rabbies and Teachers as we give to his Holiness.</p>
            <p>Therefore to make them your own, and to execute your designs the better, you must vomit out Flames and Sulpher against the Pope, declaim against Popery and Bishops; cry up Liberty of Conscience, and decry Idolatry and Superstition; you must insinuate to them, that their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Laws are in danger, and Arbitrary Power with a strong hand is coming to enslave them; you must feed them with strange fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies strongly fomented and agitated by unheard of Plots, set on foot to destroy Religion and the Nation.</p>
            <p>And the better to encourage them, you must tell them, that now is the time to retrieve the good old Case; and if the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts</hi> warred for a few Dogs, <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> and the <hi>Switzers</hi> for a Cart-load of Sheep-skins, how much are they concern'd stoutly to stand for their Covenant. Insinuate to them that they are obliged to renounce their Baptism before their Covenant, these are excellent Topicks, and will be Musick and Charms to their enchanted ears. By this means we shall gain as many Proselites as the Devil in the Northern Coasts doth Subjects, by making them invulnerable; and then you may infuse and distill what Doctrines or Principles you shall think fit, into those holy and inspired Vessels.</p>
            <p n="35">35. You must study to deboach the People, teach them to contemn God, villifie the supreme Magistrate, and to hate all Religion and Justice (as you have made a fair progress to your eternal Glory) then they are capable (as soft Wax) of any impression; you may gradually infuse the principles of the Catholick Religion into them, that which they refused to close with in the gross, they may receive by retail; and be assured when an Instrument is distuned, you may set it to any Key; proceed in this holy work, we dare promise you the Popes blessing. Catholicks must be now in the predicament of action, for they have been too long in the Category of passion; if the People will not be seduced by the Canon Law, they must be reduced by the Law of the Cannon, therefore you must, like the Statute of <hi>Apollo,</hi> have a Lance in one hand, and a Harp in the other, that is, courage to awe on the one side, and sweetness to oblige on the other; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World is but a frame of Engines, whereunto you must be the Wheel.</p>
            <p n="36">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101628:13"/>36. If any Kingdom (whose Subjects are Heretical) shall descend or come unto a Catholick Prince, the Hereticks there are to be rooted out; and all Laws or Edicts made in favour of their Religion, must be nulled and rescinded, as reproaches and scandals to the Catholick Church; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Arch-duke of <hi>Austria</hi> did like a great and worthy Prince, when on the Eighth of <hi>December</hi> 1609. by his Edict he commanded all the Churches and Houses of the Hereticks in his Dominions to be destroied and blown up with Powder; the dead Bodies of Hereticks to be digged up and burnt, which, to his great renown, was accordingly executed. But it will not be safe to banish or suppress all Sects at once, that may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperate and unite them all against you; but it's to be done gradually, beginning first with the Quakers (who are like a Taylors Goose, hot, but heavy) then with the Anabaptists (which are the very Scavengers of Schism;) after them, with the Independants, and then with the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters; thus you may safely act, for all these Sects do perfectly hate one another, and each will be pleased at the banishment or destruction of those they hate; and the remaining Party (the other Sects being ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished or destroyed) will not be considerable in power to give any great trouble or make resistance; thus our sacred Colledge in <hi>Moravia, Anno</hi> 1622. first began to banish the Anabaptists, then the Calvenists, then they thrust out the Lutherans; howsoever remember that your Laws against Hereticks be writ in blood not in Milk; and those Hereticks which are obstinate and will not submit to the Catholick Church, let them wear the <hi>San Benito;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>San Beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> is a yellow Garment, with a Red-cross be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and behind, painted full of Devils Faces; a thing of the greatest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour that may be.</note> you must be severe in the discipline, otherwise they will never be reduced.</p>
            <p n="37">37. The Catholick Religion, if it cannot be introduced into Heretical Kingdoms or Dominions by the means and arts abovesaid, it must be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by an Army, Fire and Sword.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Scilicet Haereticos ferro, flammaque petendos</l>
               <l>Stat Capitolini sententia fixa Tonantis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It will be a great Instance of your wisdom and care of the Catholick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, to have a considerable body of an Army in pay to execute your designs, as the Jesuits by their dextrous management have had in <hi>Hungary, Bohemia, Poland,</hi> and other parts; you may be sure, that when you shall break out into action (the Kingdom and Dominions being debauched, as above directed) all the Bravo's, Hectors, Atheists, Debauches, Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers, and Need-mites will join with you in hopes to better their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which must needs be a great Party.</p>
            <p>The better to strengthen your selves and Party, it will be prudence, as the Congregators did in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to Associate and enter into a Covenant, that whosoever should molest, trouble, or hurt any of their Members, the fact should be reputed hainous against the whole body of them all; by this device you will get to your Party many persons who are indebted, and Male-contents, which will make use of this Doctrine by way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. That your interest may be the more strengthened in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, you must give Offices and Employments of trust to all those of your own Party, or which are discontented with the present Government; by this trick you may twist your obligations so close together, that you may make good use of it afterwards, as it was dextrously contrived in the late
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101628:13"/> Troubles 1641. in <hi>England;</hi> therefore it's observable how careful we have been to reduce Heretical Kingdoms and States (for the good of their Souls) to the Catholick Faith.</p>
            <p n="38">38. When the People have suffered and been oppressed by Male-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of some chief Favourites and Councellours to the Prince, it hath been the practice amongst Princes to preserve themselves from popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar displeasure, to deliver them into the hands of the People (to be made Monuments of Justice) as the Authors of all their Calamities and Miseries. Thus <hi>Tiberius</hi> dealt with his Favourite <hi>Sejanus, Henry</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> with <hi>George Preston,</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> with <hi>Tigellinus.</hi> But in case any great Minister of State (who is looked upon by the People to be the source of all their Misery and Infelicity) shall be impeached by your Instruments of which you must alwaies be provided) you must insinuate into the Prince, that it's not safe to suffer such a person to be ravished from him, if he doth he will never have any to serve or advise him, or to stand up for his interest; such or the like insinuations must be used, which may work upon the Prince, if he doth not give a compliance to his People, it may beget a discontent in them, if not, a Rupture: what advantage his, Holiness will make by fishing in troubled Waters, your own experience can tell you.</p>
            <p n="39">39. When any action is designed or committed, which may be fatal or destructive to the publique, some Holy Brother, or other persons of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence must be employed (which have power with the People) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, or cry it up; or at least, to put such a good colour and varnish upon it, that the People may not be distempered at it.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the learned Dean <hi>Richard Shaw</hi> defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and justified in <hi>Guild-hall, London,</hi> and at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Cross,</hi> the unlawful and tyrannical Usurpation of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third. The Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> who unjustly murthered the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> fearing he might justly purchase the displeasure of the <hi>French</hi> King, and the hatred of <hi>France,</hi> employed <hi>John Petie</hi> a famous Divine, not only to excuse, but also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and allow the execution thereof in many publique Sermons.</p>
            <p>Nay, let the Enterprise be never so pernicious or monstrous, it will find some Advocates to defend it. Did not his Holiness Pope <hi>Sextus</hi> the Fifth, commend the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> and that it was an action well-pleasing to God, and that the Fryer was set on work by divine Inspiration. Did not <hi>Milton</hi> and <hi>Goodwin</hi> commend the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the First of <hi>England?</hi> And the <hi>Parisan</hi> Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre, <hi>Anno</hi> 1572. wanted not Defendants; therefore dwindle not away your time in pettie hazards; lay nothing at stake but Kingdoms and Principalities, and such as may add glory to the <hi>Vatican;</hi> to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise is but <hi>Phrygian</hi> like to play an after Game; the gallantry of that <hi>Spaniard</hi> was excellent, <hi>Hagase el Milagro Yhagato Mohoma, Let us have our desires, though the Devil or Turk be our Instruments or Assistants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do therefore earnestly commend unto your care, that when you have grand Villany in designs, that your Instruments to effect it, be such as have been trained up in the School of Iniquity, and well practiced in Wickedness; otherwise, if they be not fitly qualified, to propound any notorious action to them; it will be a <hi>Mormo</hi> to fright them, whereas to one that is thorough paced in wickedness, it will seem and be embraced as a meritorious act; for people are first to be well instructed in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101628:14"/> of Villany, before they be Graduates and commence in Iniquity: they must be taught to digest Mites before they will swallow Camels; therefore it was well designed to propound to <hi>D.</hi> the killing of <hi>S.</hi> before the Assassination of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second of <hi>England;</hi> for by doing the one he had been well prepared for the acting of the other; and in case he had refused to commit the Assassination; then you might safely have discovered the Murder, for the Criminal after the Villany done for ever is your Slave or Sacrifice, but dishonest and base minded men, such as have cheated the State, are the fittest persons to be confided in, and to Associate with in danger.</p>
            <p n="40">40. If you have any thing in projection, which may raise any fumes of Jealousie in the heads of the People, it will be prudence in you to make solemn Vows and Protestations to them of the candor and integrity of your actions (let your intentions be what they will) there are many good natured people who will believe you: you must learn to guild over your actions with holy Professions and good words, as Pyhsitians do their Pills, that they may be swallowed the better; you must not be like the People of <hi>Quinbaja,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Peru,</hi> which have their heads in their Breasts; for then your tongues would be too near your Hearts; you must be sure to keep them at a distance.</p>
            <p>Imitate the prudent Fox who profest he came only to hear the Cock sing, but when by his craft he had once got hold of him the case was altred.</p>
            <p n="41">41. If publique presures or affronts be done unto you, its safer to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble your displeasure then to sally into passion; by the first you may obtain your ends: but by the last you will assuredly be disappointed; Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the buckler as well as the Sword, so you will be as good at suffering as at acting; but be not indebted unto any man in injurie: make present payment if possible, and with full interest, if you be not powerful enough to contract the might of his Power; its prudence to use all industry to gain his favour, this will remove all Suspitions and jealousies and give you means to work your ends upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caesar Borgia</hi> did his business better by lulling <hi>Vitelluz</hi> a sleep, then to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard all with the Chance of Fortune; though <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th. of <hi>France</hi> did perfectly hate <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> yet he held a good Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondency with him and carried fair, but imployed others privatly to work his Ruine.</p>
            <p n="42">42. Its not safe to Communicate your designs or secrets to any but to the greatest confident, for if they which are concerned will give, your designs are certainly betrayed, therefore give no Faith to the promises of any Man; for believe us, one Perch of Performance is worth the whole Land of Promise; and if any Person shall come to the knowledge of your designs from whom there is fear of discovery, he is to be done to Death; <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth of <hi>France</hi> caused a Gentleman, a great favourite of his Brother the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> to be assassinated because the King perceived that he had a Suspition of the intended Massacre of the <hi>Hugonots;</hi> therefore trust none without the Sacrament for secrecy (which is sufficient tye upon the Souls of such Persons as have any sense of Honour or Tast of Heaven) but in Case any Persons shall be Questioned as Conspirators in the Plot; and shall therefore be Sentenced to Death (let them be never so guilty) they must at their Execution profess their Innocency to the People: call
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101628:14"/> God and Angels to testifie their integrity; and that they are as Innocent as the Child New Born. And this is to be acted with the greatest Assevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Protestations Immaginable, and to that purpose certain formula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may be drawn up, and all this may be done or said by them without the least Colour of Sin, if you grant them their Pardon before hand, for their so saying and doing: this will add much to the Catholick interest; for some of the People will think they dye Martyrs, and others thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may become Proselites to the Catholick Church; Howsoever many of them will conceive they dye unjustly by reason of their Protestations which they make, and Pious ejaculations which they send up to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="43">43. Its imprudence to stand upon niceties or the Punctilio's of honour, but by any means you must attain your ends; therefore <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> (whose Ambition was the Empire) generously entred into the Camp of <hi>Lepidus</hi> (who had the guard of <hi>Rome</hi>) and seized upon his Person, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived him of all his Honours, and confined him to the City, though he was his Confederate and Triumvirate; it was no blemish to <hi>Caesars</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, because it was in order to his Grandeur, for all remorse and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments which have not the way to the main design are to be removed; <hi>Agathocles</hi> being Praetor of <hi>Syracuse,</hi> and intending to make himself Prince thereof, assembled the People together, and the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Syracuse,</hi> as if he had something to advise with them belonging to the Common Wealth; upon a sign given caused his Souldiers to kill the <hi>Senators</hi> and the Richest of the People, and so gained the Principalitie of that City to himself; it was an act of great Glory, and will triumph in the Annals of the World; if <hi>Alexander</hi> had boggled at invading other mens Kingdoms, he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wept for the Scarcitie of Worlds.</p>
            <p>You must not stand upon those trifling things Conscience and Honour; there is nothing more unhappy or unprosperous to great undertakings than a Coy and Squemish Conscience: acknowledge no honesty or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion but what is Subservient to your designs; the more execrable Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanyes you act, it will pass amongst the rabble for Extraordinary Zeal; and you will be looked upon as a singular worthy, whom God had raised up to support the cause: your Conscience like <hi>Fortunatus</hi> purse must be full of Gold and Self-ends; if you will have your name swell and look Big in the Rolls of fame, you must be bold and daring; in the middle course there is no glory nor safety, a fortunate wickedness is a vertue; and a sin robbed with Success deserves a triumph.</p>
            <p>The foundation of <hi>Rome</hi> was Rapine, the superstructures Ambition; and the Walls of it were Cemented with Blood: and shall the Church there be less glorious having so many blessed means? the most crimson and Scarlet sins (being acted in <hi>ordine ad Spiritualia</hi>) add beauty and lustre to it, and will be looked upon in the <hi>Ethicks</hi> of that Church as Cardinal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; therefore take all opportunities to advance your designs; and where you do not find opportunities your wisdom must make them; make no criticism between just and unjust, they are but the Needle work of Idle Brains; he that is in the high way to Honour, is never out of the road to Justice, and you know, <hi>Qui aver le profit, aver le honeur; Caesar</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in order to a Crown slighted those Oathes by which he had obliged his obedience to the Roman <hi>Senate;</hi> and those who Massacred 70000 Protestants in <hi>France</hi> on Saint <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Day though they were Guests invited, received the Popes thanks, and were rewarded with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101628:15"/> many of his Spiritual graces: The first steps to power are always the most difficult, but when that is once entred on, there will not be wanting means and instruments to increase and establish it.</p>
            <p n="44">44. All Children (which possible) are to be Spirited, and sent into <hi>Seminaries</hi> beyond Seas; so careful hath his Holiness been, that there are five Colledges erected for the Instructions of the <hi>English.</hi> 1. At <hi>Doway.</hi> 2. At <hi>Rome,</hi> erected by Pope <hi>Gregory.</hi> The 3. At <hi>Valladolet</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> erected by King <hi>Philip</hi> the Second. 4. At <hi>Lovaine</hi> in <hi>Brabant.</hi> 5. At <hi>Rhemes</hi> in <hi>Campaine,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Guise.</hi> When they are perfectly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in their Arts, then they are to be sent back into their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to give Intelligence of the Affairs there, and to gain Proselytes to their Church, and to turmoil the State as they see Occasion.</p>
            <p n="45">45. It's our Glory as well as our Duty to advance the Catholick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest; you must insinuate your selves into the Courts of Princes, under them get some Office or Employment; if you cannot by your Arts effect that, then you must place your selves in the Service of some great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as Grooms, Butlers, or Coach-men, or get to be Teachers in some Separate Congregations (as there are many of our Society amongst them) you must appear great Zelots and Professors; you must Learn the knack of Canting, be well studied in the Mummery of the <hi>Quaker,</hi> the Gibbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge of the <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> and in the seeming Sanctity of the <hi>Independent;</hi> you must cock your Eyes, put on a Mortified Countenance, and whine to the well-affected People with abundance of <hi>Ha's, Oh's,</hi> and <hi>O's;</hi> you must tell them, that what you declare unto them, is agreeable to Gods Secret Will, but touch not upon the Revealed, for the most prime Saint understands that well.</p>
            <p>And we must tell you the Tone, Whining, Gesticulations, and a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance with a Religious wry look like a <hi>Persian</hi> Alphabet, will more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Rabble, than the Learning of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or the Eloquence of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the better to advance your Designs, you must now and then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be transported into Fits of quaking and tremblings, into raptures, extasies, and abreptions of Mind, as that good Man, Major <hi>Weier</hi> did in his Field Conventicles in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Illuminated Brethren will presently believe that you have the income of the Spirit, which will be an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Magnetism to make a strong Verticity in them to the point of any Design.</p>
            <p n="46">46. You must insinuate your selves into the Richest People, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially into Women, who are easily seduced, and then their Husbands and Children must be Ruled by them, and if there be occasion, they will serve you to their very Bodkins and Thimbles, as you have had Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the late Troubles in <hi>England:</hi> You must fix your selves in the most Opulent and Rich Towns and Cities; for you may observe the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Whigs in <hi>Scotland</hi> (our fellow-labourers) who have with much discretion Planted themselves in <hi>Fife</hi> and the West of <hi>Scotland</hi> (as the Non-Conforming Ministers have done in <hi>London</hi>) where many Rich Traders and Heritors Live: But for the <hi>High-Lands,</hi> and other poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> their Souls are not worth the whistling or owning for want of Silver and Gold: When you have gotten a Reputation, for your Godliness and Zeal every Family will think it self Sanctified with your Spiritual Conversation, and will requite you with white and yellow Blessings.</p>
            <p n="47">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101628:15"/>47. Set up as many Teachers as you can, the greater the Number of them, the more Proselytes they will gain; Court the Rabble, and you will never want Disciples, and they being once inspired, you may Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them upon any Design, as <hi>Ericus (Ventosi Pile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi> King of <hi>Swedland,</hi> did the Winds, by turning off his Cap. By this means you may much advance the Apostolick See by giving Intelligence to the Superiours, for the managing and betraying of all Designs, as they please. And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that you Ruine those you cannot Proselyte.</p>
            <p>But in case all fail, then you must be able to work upon some Trade, of which there are upwards of 3000 in and about <hi>London,</hi> which are looked upon as Phanaticks, but in reality they are Jesuites and Priests; nay, some part of their Congregations are <hi>Romanists,</hi> though the rest know it not, which are taken to be Godly and Holy Professors: You know Father <hi>Brown</hi> the Jesuit, who Preached seven Years to the Whigs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was looked upon as a Godly and Zealous Man, yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared at his Death, that he had Preached to them at their Field Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, as down-right Popery as ever he Preached in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="48">48. Be continually designing, something may happen by chance beyond expectation; the Ape little thought by putting on his Masters Cap, to Cure him of a Pleurisie: <hi>Domitian,</hi> rather than destroy nothing, would kill Flies; it's better to play small Game, than set out; when there are many Male-Contents in a State, some Accident or other may be every day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but put it amongst the Memoires of your Cabinet, that what you cannot do by fair Compliance, you must effect by the Sword; therefore the Resolution of Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Second was admirable, who being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased with <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12 of <hi>France,</hi> and Marching out with an Army against the <hi>French,</hi> took St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys and hurled them into the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> saying, since St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys will not quiet mine Enemies, I'le try what St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sword will do: For though Wise Actions are begotten un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Mercury,</hi> yet in case of Opposition, they must be brought forth by assistance of <hi>Mars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let Interest be the Card by which you Stere, and the Apostolick See the Harbour to which your Designs do arrive.</p>
            <p>It's a good piece of Prudence to Stere your Designs according as the Wind sits for most Advantage: Thus <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> wrote many things before he was Pope, which, when he had once obtained the Triple Crown, he censured as dangerous, saying, <hi>Pius</hi> Condemned that which <hi>Aeneas</hi> thought good.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Pensioners about Great Persons must be made, for they are the fittest Instruments to facilitate or promote any Design; without them we are little better than a Bird without Wings: If we manage our Designs dextrously, all Places of Trust and Dignities may be disposed of accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our pleasures, and conferred upon such Persons as will best serve the Catholick Interest; <hi>Pillulae Aureae</hi> are the best Physick, for they ever work safely, and will remove all Obstructions; therefore it must be your care to have a good Fund and Bank of Money to Reward Persons for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Services, and to Recompence all Informers, Spies, Agents, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers to betray their nearest Friends and Relations; remember that Intelligence is the right Eye of Prudence.</p>
            <p n="50">50. Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks, for in every Contract there must be <hi>actus contra actum,</hi> or <hi>quid pro quo;</hi> and as Hereticks have no Faith
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101628:16"/> to give, so no Faith is to be kept with them; if therefore any Protestants upon some Promises to them made, turn Papists, you need not perform with them, but they are to be told that they might well content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and thank his Holiness that their Souls were brought into a safe Religion: And Hereticks are no otherwise to be dealt with, than we deal with Children or Mad-men, give them fair Promises (till we get the Sword or Knife out of their Hands) without any regard of Performance. You know Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> when she was like to be laid aside for her Religion, what great Matters she Promised the <hi>Suffolk</hi> Men, if they would Arm in Favour of her, which they did, but being ascended the Throne, she ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kept her Faith with them, but there were more of that Countrey Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for their Religion, and were undone, than of any other County in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>O. Cromwel</hi> never kept any Oath or Protestation, when it was for his Advantage to break them; it's for Merchants to keep their Word and Promise, not for you, who must make it your chief End to propagate the Faith.</p>
            <p n="51">51. If you have committed any dis-ingenious or Villanous Act (though in order to propagate the Faith) if it be decryed, the better to clear your selves, and preserve your Reputation, you may safely charge some Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or Schismatick with the Fact (you know the Cuckow lays her Brood in other Birds Nests.) Therefore <hi>Creswell</hi> and <hi>Curtis;</hi> Jesuites who were Active and great Instruments of the Massacre in <hi>Paris,</hi> observing that the Fact was abominable and abhorred by many, they very ingeniously laid it to the Charge of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Calvenists</hi> there.</p>
            <p>The Powder Plot (which was the work of Darkness) coming to light, the Jesuites very discreetly cast the whole Design and Contrivance of that Plot upon <hi>Cecil,</hi> the then Secretary of State, and it was managed with that Art, and had such a handsom Gloss and fine Paint put upon it, that at this day some look upon it as a Political Scare-crow, and others do not believe that there was any such Plot.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Francis</hi> the Second of <hi>France</hi> dyed, the Emissaries of our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Council gave out (contrary to the Opinion of the Physitians) that he was Poysoned by the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> which was done to render them odious, and that they might the better drive on their own Designs.</p>
            <p>We must tell you, that you have Acted beyond a Prodigy, in casting the Infamy of the last Plot of killing the King, and subverting the Church and State of <hi>England,</hi> upon the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> there, who (by reason of their former Acting) in the Judgment of some Persons do not stand very clear, but do conceive that they have cast the scandal upon the Jesuites, that they might be looked upon as great Patrons and Assertors of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liberty, and so come into Play again themselves, that they might Act the same things, by other Arts and Methods.</p>
            <p n="52">52. If any Discontent happen between an Heretical King and People, it must be your care and study to boyl it up to that height, that it may easily turn into a Rebellion. Zeal is the Flint, and Ambition the Steel, out of which the sparks thereof do first kindle; when they begin to Arm, mix your selves with the Souldiers on both sides, so you may by your Arts continue the War as long as you please, and commit what Spoils and Plunders you shall think fit; you may betray Towns and Castles, Ruine Churches (to propagate the Gospel, as it hath been formerly done) and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101628:16"/> destroy Hereticks and Schismaticks, as the Jesuites did in <hi>Moravia, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, Austria, Styria, Hungaria,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> to their great Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But be sure you destroy and spoil the Universities (which are the Seminaries of Heresie) as the Holy Fathers the Jesuites did <hi>Caroline</hi> Academy near <hi>Prague,</hi> and one at <hi>Vienna</hi> sometime before; you must en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the young Souldiers in Christs Army Royal, to Fight the Lords Battel, and to be forward to shew their Zeal to the Good Old Cause, and their Countries well-fare; you must declare unto them the Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of their Adversaries to have introduced Popery and Tyranny into the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But howsoever let the Good Old Cause be the general Doctrine, Fight manfully, the Exhortation, kill the Heir, and take Possession, the use and application of all: Make the Hereticks believe they do God good Service in destroying one another: This Holy Rhetorick and Gospel encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are beyond the Influence of a <hi>Teles-man,</hi> and the best Philter for a Rebellion.</p>
            <p>You must appoint your General in this Spiritual Warfare, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to carry on the work of the Lord, we do Advise you to Consecrate him, as we usually do such Persons as are by us Ordered, for the Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Assassination of a King or Prince, the Formulary whereof is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: <hi>Go on, thou Elect Son of God, take here the Sword of</hi> Gideon, <hi>the Sword of</hi> Jeptha, <hi>the Sword of</hi> Samson, <hi>the Sword of</hi> David, <hi>the Sword of the</hi> Maccabees; <hi>go on, thou Blessed of the Lord, be of good Courage, and the Lord strengthen your Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done, you must cry up the Interest of the King or Prince, and declare what a great and Glorious King you will make him; but when you have Foraged the Nation, enriched your selves, and impoverished all, then you must so order your Affairs, that the People may prevail; then the King or Prince, contrary to all your Vows, Protestations, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants (which you have made) must be called <hi>Coram nobis,</hi> his Power and Revenue must be dwindled to nothing, his best Friends and Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents must be Ruined; but if the People will have a King, let him be like <hi>Sancho Panco,</hi> who was made Governour of the Island <hi>Barataria,</hi> but had no Authority or Power; you may suffer him to wear a Sword by his side, because he is a Gentleman, but not upon any occasion whatsoever to draw it, hang a Lock at his Hilt, but keep you the Keys.</p>
            <p>Thus our Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> (being influenced by Missinaries from our Holy Conclave) took all Power of Arms into their own Hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, as they rightly declared, the Kings Castles and Strengths are the Keys of the Realm, and they knew no Reason to the contrary but that they might keep their own Keys; therefore though you give him the Name of King, yet take all Authority to your selves.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101628:17"/>
            <p>If at any time the Prince hath Occasion for Moneys to support the Honour and Interest of the Nation, deal with him, as others do with their Children, giving them Gold in a Box, which they must not finger, only please themselves with its ratlings; by this means the People may make themselves a Negative Vote in Peace and War, which may be of good Advantage to us.</p>
            <p>But if you do give Money, let it be upon some grand Consideration, that the Prince may part with ten times more of his Royal Power and Rights of the Crown than the Money is worth; by this Art, you will so clip and pare the Prerogative, that in a short time he will be a <hi>Ludovicus Nihil,</hi> a <hi>John Sans terre,</hi> or at the best, a Duke of <hi>Venice:</hi> For the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative and Liberty of the Subjects are like unto two Buckets in a Well, as one goes up, the other comes down.</p>
            <p>It will be Prudence in you to imitate the crafty Fryer, who desired to his Dinner only the Liver of a Capon, and a Roasted Piggs Head, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full well, that if he got those, he would not want his part of the Pig and Capon too.</p>
            <p>If the Laws of the Land be not extensive enough for to serve your purposes, you must piece them our with Arbitrary Ordinances and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal Law (as they did in the late Troubles in <hi>England</hi>) which was then grown to that height, that the Council of War, General and Judge Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate of the Army did usually send forth Instructions to stay Suits, and release Judgments at Law, or else to attend the Council of War where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever they sat, or to shew cause to the contrary; and they were Obeyed, when the Ordinances and Commands of the Judges were neglected and slighted.</p>
            <p>But all this you must Act under pretence of Conscience, Christian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and for the establishing of Property in your Goods and Estates, good and holy pretences will justifie the worst Actions, therefore it will be requisite to put a fair Complexion on all your Enterprizes; some Holy and Evangelical Doctrines must be thought on which may serve as an Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brella to all your Designs: It's a great Advantage to be a good <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> and Spiritual Jugler.</p>
            <p>But in case you cannot effect your Designs, then let some Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Catholick Prince be called into the Assistance of the Weaker side, and so both Parties will become a Prey to him, and by that means the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion may be established. The <hi>Phoenicians</hi> and <hi>Boeotians</hi> having Wars between them, the <hi>Boeotians</hi> being disabled, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed in Aid of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who came with his Army, washed the Countrey of the <hi>Phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and reduced them to Servitude, and gained to himself the whole Countrey of the <hi>Boeotians;</hi> this may be to good purpose Practised: It's not <hi>tanti</hi> to the <hi>Vatican,</hi> who is Supream, so he be for the Catholick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest; as for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Common People, they will chose rather the present State with Security, than to recover the old with Danger; you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101628:17"/> may with a little Rhetorick perswade them to be quiet, telling them they are designed to defend the Capitol.</p>
            <p n="53">53. If any Person be a great Favourite to a Prince or People, if he be not a Friend to the Catholick Interest, he must be taken down, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way under pretence of some Honourable Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; then by your Segacity you may either cast him from his present Honour, or else he may be made less Potent, or some Friend to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Colledge placed in his room; therefore <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> Acted like himself, when he perswaded <hi>M. Anthony</hi>'s absence from <hi>Rome,</hi> to go into <hi>Egypt,</hi> it was to bring him into Contempt, and Usher in his Ruine. And nothing did more contribute to the Dignity and Grandeur of <hi>Agathocles</hi> in <hi>Syracuse,</hi> than when by his Arts <hi>Sesostratus</hi> was removed from thence, who was the greatest Obstruction of his Designs. The Prudence and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity of <hi>Francis Stozza</hi> was very commendable (and in many cases to good purpose may be practised by you) who being desirous to remove <hi>Troilus</hi> and <hi>Peter Brunorus,</hi> two Eminent Commanders, from the Service of <hi>Alphonso</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> framed a Letter, in the end whereof he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that without delay they should put in execution the Consultation which had passed betwixt them; which he conveyed in such manner, that it fell into the Hands of the King, who understanding the Contents of it, sent them thereupon as Prisoners to <hi>Catalogne:</hi> By this means he deprived him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self of two Excellent Commanders, and gave his Enemy that content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he looked for.</p>
            <p n="54">54. If there be a Heretick Prince who hath Faithful and Prudent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants about him, by your Insinuations and Arts they must be brought into disfavour, and so removed, by this means you will assuredly bring Ruine and Destruction to that Prince.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Valentinian</hi> having caused <hi>Aetius</hi> his Faithful Servant to be Executed, he was himself in a short time after slain by <hi>Maximus,</hi> a <hi>Roman Patrician,</hi> whose Treacherous Attempts, during the Life of <hi>Aetius,</hi> were so over awed, that they durst never offer so much as once to shew themselves. And King <hi>Richard</hi>'s Banishing of <hi>Mowbray</hi> upon the difference between him and <hi>Bullingbrook,</hi> was his own Deposing.</p>
            <p n="55">55. Change and Alteration in Government must be made gradually, you must cunningly temporize, and suffer the People insensibly and by degrees to drop into Slavery, and not Oppress them all at once, as <hi>Julius Caesar</hi> did; they must be bound by Benefits, or by severity made sure from Offending.</p>
            <p>And the only Course to make Greatness stand firmly, is to receive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Power under a Title not offensive; therefore <hi>O. Cromwell,</hi> that great <hi>Mustapha</hi> of Sedition (though an eminent promoter of the Triple
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101628:18"/> Crown, and our great Friend) would not receive a Crown himself, or admit of the Name of King (for that would have disobliged his own Party) but the specious Name of Protector to please the Rabble.</p>
            <p>And the better to secure your selves from Factions and Conspiracies, you must rather fear those to whom you have done over great Favours, than those you have much injured; for these want Opportunity, the other do not; and the Ambition of Command is always as much or more than the desire of Revenge: But never trust any you have injured, for a Lion is a Lion, though he shrinks up his paws.</p>
            <p n="56">56. Count it better to be Successful than Just. <hi>Rome</hi>'s Second Founder, <hi>Camillus Scipio,</hi> that great Scourge of <hi>Carthage,</hi> was Disgraced, and <hi>M. Cariolanus</hi> Banished, only because their Worth and Vertue had lifted them above the Ordinary pitch of Subjects.</p>
            <p>There are not two more Fortunate Properties, than to have somewhat of the Fool, and not too much of the Honest. Remember Count <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damore,</hi> how he managed the Catholick Interest with King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> If you be truly just, Living amongst so many Men which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just, you will assuredly be Ruined.</p>
            <p>It's a great Instance of Wisdom, and sometimes the best Expedient to promote Designs, to Act the Part of a Fool, by that means you lie out of the reach of Jealousie, and none will suspect you; be sure to keep Formality above board, but your Prudence under deck; make not your selves a Body of Crystal for others to look through you; but be like a Coffer with a double bottom, when others look into it, being opened, they see not what is within it on the sudden and at once: Never open your selves but with an half light, and for Advantage; <hi>Giges</hi> Ring was his Wisdom, whereby he understood others, and was reserved himself. If my Shirt, said <hi>Metellus,</hi> knew my Mind, I would burn it. Before I told you of this, I was Emperour; but now you are, said <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, when he discovered his Designs upon the seventeen Provinces, to his Friend the Duke of <hi>Luxenburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you have employed any Person in a Mischievous Design, if he doth not effect it according to your desires, or there is fear that he will Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, your safest Course will be to give him a Baccado. You must not perplex your selves with any Niceties of Conscience; if it be to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the Faith, it's Just; and a Noble Action is its own Herald: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you will have the right Knack of doing business, you must ease your selves of those two grand Remoraes to all Honourable Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings▪ Religion and Conscience. Hold nothing Impious or Wicked which is for the Advantage of your Designs. We must Commend the Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity and Heroick Genius of the Noble <hi>Parthians,</hi> who acknowledged no Honesty or Religion, but what was for their Private Interest. Father <hi>Richard Walpool,</hi> a Jesuit, employed <hi>Squire, Anno</hi> 1595. to Poyson
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101628:18"/> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> But for some Months hearing no News of the Queens Death, <hi>Walpool</hi> supposing that <hi>Squire</hi> had doubled with him; thereupon, to be Revenged of him, he sent an <hi>English-man</hi> to inform the Queen of the Conspiracy of <hi>Squire</hi> to Poyson her (though <hi>Squire</hi> was very Active to effect it, and had pursued his Instructions) <hi>Squire</hi> was thereupon seized, and Consessed the whole matter, for which he was Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted. This was looked upon by the Sacred Colledge as a Prudent and Righteous Act in <hi>Walpool,</hi> and he had their Reward and Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="57">57. Predictions and Prophesies are of Admirable Use to deceive the People, and serve Ends; therefore such Predictions must be framed as may accommodate Designs, and please Vulgar Fancies, and your selves must be the Oracles: The People are to be made believe (as you may put any thing into their Creed) that Heaven is of the Plot, and concerned in the Enterprize for their good. Thus <hi>Lysander,</hi> projecting the change of Government of <hi>Sparta,</hi> would engage the Gods in the Design, and corrupted the Priests to forge Oracles for the same. <hi>Catiline,</hi> to inflame <hi>Lentulus</hi> to Burn <hi>Rome,</hi> fed his Ambitious Soul with some dark Oracle out of the <hi>Sybils</hi> Leaves: The Multitude will easily comport with that Design, which they believe had some Signature from Heaven, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced from above: If Success doth attend but one Prediction, it will give Credit and Reputation to the rest, and make them all Authentick. And sometimes the Vulgar, who are more Superstitious than Religious, will themselves either find or frame a Prediction for every great event.</p>
            <p>How patiently did the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> sustain their Losses, and the Burning of the Metropolis of <hi>England,</hi> when they Read it was fore-told so many Years before, and by consequence Predestinated?</p>
            <p>Therefore you must be well furnished with those or the like Tools upon all Occasions, for they are of singular use to manage any Design: How was <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> influenced to ascend the Throne, when the Oracle <hi>(Nostradamus)</hi> insinuated to them,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le Roydes Isles sera chasse par force</l>
                     <l>Misa son lieu qui de Roy ne aura signe:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A King of Islands shall be Banish'd, and</l>
                     <l>An Ʋpstart <hi>Jack</hi> by force shall Rule the Land.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That Image of Wax, or Head of Earth, framed by Necromancy (in King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's Reign) at <hi>Oxford,</hi> which at a time spake these words,
<q>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:101628:19"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Caput decidetur; Caput elevatur,</l>
                     <l>Pedes elevabantur supra Caput.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Head shall be cut off, the Head shall be lifted up;</l>
                     <l>The Feet shall be lifted above the Head.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Had wondrous effects; and be assured nothing is more capable of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion than the Vulgar, if you know their Genius rightly, and Prudently to manage them. And you must know, that doubtful Oracles are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Interpreted to the desires of the Interested Faction: That dubious Letter,
<q>Edwardum occidere Nobite timere bonum est;</q> To kill <hi>Edward</hi> do not fear is a good thing, was so well understood by Sir <hi>Thomas Gourney,</hi> Sir <hi>John Maltravers,</hi> that the Murder of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second was Resolved.</p>
            <p>But whensoever you have designed any Notorious Villany, as the Assas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinating of a Prince, or Firing of a great City, or the like, you may with good success fore-tell, that about such a day it will happen out, and come to pass; as <hi>F. Cammolet</hi> Prophesied when he had designed the Assas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sination of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great of <hi>France,</hi> that in a little time, the King will be slain. And the fore-telling of the Conflagration of <hi>London</hi> (when it was contrived by our Sacred Conclave) was well Acted; and be assured that the Jesuitologers can more certainly Prognosticate the Death of any Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than any Astrologer; therefore you must apply your selves to this Art, for it will make you considerable in the World, and Men will think that you are of the Privy Council to Heaven, and like <hi>Moses,</hi> had been with God in the Mount; howsoever you will be looked upon as Oracles, and the Rabble will bow to your Wisdom, and Sacred Spirit of Prophecy. The fore-telling by his Holiness of the Victory gained by the Christians at the Battel of <hi>Lepanto:</hi> And the defeat of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army at <hi>Preston,</hi> by <hi>James Michael,</hi> purchased them a very great Reputation, and their Memory will be Celebrated by Posterity for it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101628:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>